all right welcome back everyone my name
is Devon Bay um I'll be presenting uh
accounting for multiscalar and conscious
psychobiological phenomena in the active
inference
Paradigm so for an overview I'm going to
be going over the Markov blanket trick
and then critiques of the marov blanket
and address how some of the previous
work of Chris fields and friston
partially addresses these critiques um
before finally going over uh problems of
consciousness new approaches and
theories on Consciousness and how these
fit within the Fe and active inference
and then provide some ways to update the
framework uh based on this
information I'm also going to uh take an
epistemological perspective on modeling
and I'll focus on how both the
conceptual mathematical formalizations
of superposition and entanglement can
maybe alleviate some of the problems
that are identified in the critiques
so
um the Markov blanket since we are on uh
limited time here um I will assume that
most of the people here are already
familiar somewhat with the marov blanket
or active inference framework um but
I'll give a brief overview of the marov
blanket focusing on some of its
mathematical Frameworks as well as some
of the Assumption assumptions implicit
within the the framework so um for the
mathematical overview given a state s of
a model it's more blanket is the set of
sufficient States within the network
needed to infer that state and it
essentially partitions autonomous and
external States and uh is helpful in
identifying which variables are
conditionally independent from each
other and expresses The Joint
probability between external and
internal States um as mediated by
blanket States so the assumptions here
is that there sparse coupling between
the different states in the mark of uh
in yeah in in the uh in the overall
system and that there is uh somewhat of
a delineation between external and Inter
internal States and uh that these
external internal States can be properly
partitioned via the marov
blanket so uh the implications here the
marov blanket is metaphysically distinct
from Pearl blankets uh at least in the
context of active inference or for
energy principle I think this was uh
raised by
um uh by uh boomberg or and and his
colleagues um in the uh in the Markov uh
in the emperor's new Markov blanket
paper um and so this essentially means
that they are
um they are uh they differentiate
themselves from Pearl blankets by nature
of their application and the frisen
blanket Itself by nature uh takes on
assumptions like the existence of
external internal sensory and active
States um and so this is the the main
sort of differentiation also uh the
frisen blanket is not providing a
metaphysics um at least uh at least in
my interpretation and so uh so we assume
here the existence of distinct states
which may be modeled um and this means
that there are distinct States which are
properly separable and that there are
either epistemological or ontological
grounds for doing so and so the main
problem here I think is that there is
not enough justification to argue that
the the marov blanket partitioning is an
epistemological or um you know in in a
more broader sense an
ontological um boundary and that is uh
you know causally um
correct or it is it causally captures is
able to causally cap capture causal
relationships between variables um
because the existence of sensory um of
sensory active in internal States um and
external States is something which can
be disputed and which I'll discuss later
on in this talk and so uh another
implication of the markco blank is is
that it allows the modeling of recursive
structures and Dynamics by use of the re
roral ization group for example which um
apparently allows to marov blanket to
capture multiscalar phenomenon um and
finally the question of whether the
marov blanket aderes to the beian O
razor um it would simply depend on the
choice of parameters for the specific
model and does not inherently implicate
the Marco
blanket so um critiques of the marov
blanket like I mentioned earlier the
ontological critique of the marov
blanket is leveraged by both brunberg
and Raja in their respective papers
although as we've seen in responses to
these papers frankly depends on the
ontological interpretation of active
inference and uh the free energy
principle and if as kerstein in his
response to bromberg's paper claims the
Markov blanket should not be interpreted
literally then this problem partially
goes away however the epistemological
status of the marov blanket is still
under question as raised in a part of
raja's paper in so far as the
explanatory power of the models under
some pressure so chiefly there's a
broader philosophical question about the
purpose of models and this is not
necessarily unique
to FP or active inference or the Markov
blanket but nevertheless since it
affects all models these are issues are
raised um are raised in in in uh in in
the context of the markup blanket as
well uh next we also see that there is a
mathematical uh problem with the
selection of Marco blanket States um
because we see that
the uh for example uh Dynamic causal
modeling in Neuroscience does not
demonstrate that uh that models provide
scientists with a plausible account of
the behavior of real world biological
systems since successful applications of
of causal modeling does not give us any
reason to believe that neural systems
plausibly for example minimize free
energy or that they are arotic active
inference systems and so uh this means
that even though the model may be
applied successfully and may predict
some uh Behavior successfully it doesn't
necessarily mean that the model is
number one an accurate representation of
what's ongoing with uh you know the
internal dynamics of the system and
number two that it would therefore be
able to capture accurately all of the
internal workings of this of the system
um and so uh so yes and on this
mathematical side as well we also see
that uran Elon published in
2023 um a paper on the constrain
disorder principle and how that would uh
possi dictate neuronal function and so
Elon points out that despite the
stochasticity exhibited by the neur
nervous systems operation there's not
necessarily a high level of control
since Randomness at the lower levels
never stops and thus it dictates a
paradigm of reaction not action by
organisms um he uses the free energy
principle but does not use it to justify
a form of active inference which would
be minimizing certainty but rather
argues that the constraint disorder
principle um uh is is more preferable
where a process of balancing disorder
and order is more inherent to systems
operation in highly Dynamic random
environments so whether all environments
are highly Dynamic and random and at
what scales this Randomness can be
asymptotically ignored becomes uh or
becomes irrelevant is still for question
however the fact that these boundaries
are not clear and in fact that they
arguably cannot be made clear for
example via the um existence of
Maxwell's demon or limits on
computability Etc should point us in the
direction of choosing better models and
better parameters for these models so
what can this tell us about uh the free
energy principle in the marov blanket
first it points to broader problems with
the free energy principle but these
still carry over um
implications uh the sorry these still
carry implications for the ways in which
the free energy principle
epistemologically treats the marov
blanket mainly to delineate uh a cross
in between scales and uh causal uh
relationships in the later portion of
this talk I'll explain why entanglement
and superposition are suitable
replacements for the marov blanket when
they actually offer a greater
flexibility without constraining the
mathematical and philosophical
operations
and notably Chris Field's paper on the
FP for generic Quantum systems makes
implicit use of the same some of the
same affordances offered by
superposition and entanglement but takes
a very specific interpretation of
quantum systems and I think limits the
flexibility of of such modeling tools by
adhering to the holographic
principle
um so uh now onto the uh
epistemological uh status of models
which I think is important to raise here
because the because the question of
whether the marov blanket can accurately
Encompass
multi-directional uh what I'll call
horizontal Pathways vertical and
horizontal Pathways even without the
presence of clear attractor States is
still under question as is the more
General Assumption of ergodicity within
the Fe framework and so um as
experimental evidence from physics shows
um systems in general not simply at
macro or micro states are afflicted by
complex Dynamics such as replica
symmetry breaking which fall into a sort
of gray area between ergodicity and
non-ergodicity and thus render the
determination of of ergodicity versus
non-ergodicity much more complicated
even with suggestions such as local
ergodicity as outlined by ramstead in uh
in the 2018
article so um I think it's important to
outline the epist ological status of
models because um it's important for
clarifying whether the marov blanket
itself is problematic within the uh the
FP framework and whether it can
potentially be reworked so from a beijan
perspective models should want to
minimize both epistemic and alator
uncertainty where epistemic uncertainty
is the reducible part of the total
uncertainty and alator uncertainty is
basically the irreducible part active
inference models therefore should
minimize uh both epistemic and alator
uncertainty um and represent possible
model configurations and parameters via
prior hypothesis space where the choice
of model is informed both by where we
believe the qual truth is located or at
least the uh the most truthful uh model
is located as well as the model
constraints so here we see um in green
is the ideal situation where we have an
ideal selection of model with some with
an ideal convergence to some truth X um
and then uh the purple shows an example
here where uh our prior hypothesis space
does not accurately Encompass the true
model and hence by extension the true
model is not included in the posterior
finally the pink shows where the
posterior does not converge to the true
model um and so this is illustrating how
problems can arise in these two areas
first the hypothesis base does not
properly Encompass the true model X
which is uh the purple or blue example
and then second the posterior space does
not properly converge to the true model
X which is our pink uh Pink example here
and so constraints on X uh depend on if
you're a realist or an anti-realist so
for example if you believe that there is
some ground truth that is universal and
um unchanging and it's you know
physically uh accessible then of course
the true model would be a a real true
model but uh if you're more of an
anti-realist then it would depend on uh
you know your your hypothesis space and
you know of course whether you believe
that troops can be can be accurately
represented or even be accessed um and
that they're Universal or whatever so
yeah is now now the question is is the
marov blanket the proper choice of
parameter for the free energy principle
and active inference so the purpose of
the marov blanket is to provide a
statistical boundary which delineates a
system from its environment and ensures
that variables are conditionally
independent um of that certain variables
are conditionally independent of other
variables in the network and it
formalizes the belief of the prior that
the system and its environment are
separate either ontologically
epistemologically physic Ally like
literally or even causally right so um
Columbo and palasio actually indict the
marov blanket and Fe active inference
model by saying that it achieves maximal
generality for minimal biological
plausibility because these boundaries
are can be drawn sort of arbitrarily and
uh even the existence of cellular um
cellular membranes for example does not
necessarily constrain causal relations
between or cross
scales so uh notably uh Noble um argues
that organisms are open systems that
operate far from equilibrium and so
again drawing from Noble's arguments uh
Elon in the 2023 paper argues that
organisms develop numerous emergent
boundaries between levels which are not
present at the single cell level so even
though they may have distinct functional
purposes boundaries like the skin
intestinal tract or even vastus medialis
depend on exchanging matter and energy
through cellular membranes and so
boundary is thus Dynamic interactive not
passive and cannot always be defined
anatomically so for example electric
gradiance and onon concentration
gradients are actively generated across
cell membranes where interactions across
boundar determine an organism's
functions uh not just parts of not just
the the composition of the boundary or
uh or the genome so of course one way
this has been explored in the free
energy principle and active inference is
via uh the sort of recursive marov
blanket but uh we see that this sort of
recursive modeling is not able to
properly capture um multiscalar
relationships and interactions
across in between boundaries where
essentially we would have uh you know um
marov blankets that are um that are
causally implicated in in more than one
uh in more than one way that that can
sorry in more than one way that can be
described by simply the repertoire of
active external um internal States uh
and sensory States
and so this is sort of where the case
for
entanglement comes into play because uh
entanglement is uh is has been argued
for as a way of causally representing
relationships between variables in uh in
biology so first of all we see that
organizational boundaries of living
systems are open and flexible such that
these boundaries need not be Co exensive
with the organism's bodily boundaries
number one so again I guess this is just
to drive home the point uh that the
Markov blanket should not be taken
literally um but we also see that
biology is inherently Quantum so uh so
these um so these uh these processes of
uh cellular differentiation for example
uh are under are fundamentally underlied
by or sorry under fundamentally you know
determined by or perhaps uh sort of
controlled by uh Quantum processes that
dictate you know um what chemical bonds
the cell is able to break for example or
how certain concentrations of of ions
for example flow across um across the
cellular membrane and the permeability
of the membrane as well can also exhibit
Quantum effects so as you know the field
of quantum biology grows I think we will
increasingly see that the quantum levels
is extremely important for dictating how
uh organisms evolve and especially if
you know um Quantum Consciousness
theories continue to gain support uh we
could see that uh Quantum processes may
also be implicated in Consciousness and
so causal entanglement addresses a sort
of
asymmetry um between what were
previously considered linear processes
um and um the sort of asymmetry across
in between scales so uh I basically
argue that causal entanglement is a
counterintuitive form of aam's Razor
because when we have entangled variables
we don't need to always explicitly
represent the dependencies of these
variables um with each other so um uh
that means that we are we can you know
in an infinite dimensional Hilbert space
or a finite dimensional Hilbert space
represent the variables uh in a way that
does not necessarily dictate uh specific
boundaries or um or constraints on these
variables which may impede the ca of
modeling of uh certain phenomena so as
the scale and complexity of the model
increases representing relationship via
entanglement becomes much more appealing
and of course uh you know Quantum
Computing also offers ways to um to
speed up um uh the the computation of of
machine learning models like act like an
active
inference so uh vti actually puts
forward a case for causal entanglement
using uh
DNA and essentially we see that uh the
in lement can serve as a form of
um uh a form of of sort of outlining the
the total the sorry the different causal
dependencies in a system without
necessarily explicating them without
putting too much emphasis on the uh the
specific properties of the causal
relationships if we know that causal
certain things are causally implement or
sorry are causally implicated then we
can take the sort of rough approach of
assuming that they might be uh you know
entangled to some degree um and so
basically entanglement can serve as a
method for
representing causal Relationships by
conflating correlation with causation
and so the um
the in the paper vei uses chromatin
structures during the interface period
of mitosis to show how and basically
show how it can be characterized in
terms of interactions between entities
at uh three different levels of
biological organization so essentially
the the parts or angles between the
linkers the uh in the chromatin and um
then uh the the chrom structure or the
topological invariant structure and then
finally the the in the feedback loop
between how the whole which is the the
overall chromatin structure depends on
context properties in the feedback loop
uh for example via histone dilation or
histone
methylation and so essentially uh we see
that they argue that DNA is a total both
a total and direct cause when being
manipulated where it is a total cause
because DNA is is implicated in its in
its own manipulation and it's also a
direct cause because um it's uh it's an
intervention on DNA will change uh will
change the the you know this the
functional structural properties of the
DNA um with with without changing
necessarily L um additional uh non lo
non-local you know properties of
whatever substrate surrounds the DNA and
so specificity still allows linear
models to capture causal relationships
in terms of you know isolating specific
variables but when we increase the scale
and complexity of these uh of the model
for example or what we include in the
model it becomes increasingly more
difficult to separate out
and to sort of distinguish okay where
exactly does a specificity
lie and so uh this takes me to this
differentiation between repertoire and
connectedness when it comes to causal
specificity so repertoire is basically
how many possibilities exist on each
side the cause side and the effect side
and we can essentially in in a modeling
context take this to mean the number of
different values that an effect variable
and a cause variable can take
meanwhile the connectedness is how many
or how the possibilities on both sides
are connected in particular relevant
ways so we can see uh again in the
modeling C test that connected
connectedness is a condition for a given
function connecting the values of cause
and effect variables and so repertoire
does not entail connectedness and
connectedness does not entail repertoire
which is important to note um because
essentially we see that
um that uh repertoire and but by
splitting causal specificity into these
two independent properties we may not be
able to compare causal relations from a
single point of view and therefore uh
you know causal entanglement will may
allow for the comparison of both without
necessarily giving up you know one one
for the other and uh and of course uh Ru
notes that you need both repertoire and
connectedness in order to come to a
complete causal understanding of you
know whatever processes are implicated
or you're examining within the system
and so the the form of entanglement
between uh you know repertoire and
connectedness um would would allow you
to express uh both of them in the system
simultaneously and potentially uh you
know um extract results from uh from
either of
them and so uh what are the practical
constraints and limitations on this uh
this approach well first of all we
should uh view we might view it as a
case similar to Quantum versus classical
Computing where as the complexity class
of the problem increases Quantum
Computing becomes more appealing so
utilizing entanglement may not be
computationally feasible right now given
Hardware constraints and um modeling
using the entanglement May aisc uh the
extraction of direct cause of
relationships but um as Noble has
pointed out and this previous
researchers have pointed out the
extraction of direct cause of
relationships is a very difficult task
and epistemologically it's not clear
whether this is even possible once the
system surpasses a uh given uh given you
know point of complexity where it's simp
where the dependencies between uh and
across scales simply become too large to
um to properly uh identify you know
direct cause or
relationships and so um essentially uh
this this entanglement approach may also
become computationally infeasible when
uh we have lots of uh you know dense
variables that are not sparsely coupled
but I think because uh you know the
Markov blanket also you know inherently
relies on the sparse coupling and sparse
coupling in neuronal Dynamics has been
shown uh entanglement can be taken as an
as a as a sort of replacement for the
marov
blanket um and so I'll just uh get into
some previous work involving the free
energy principle in quantum mechanics so
Fields uh Chris Fields integrated Ed
Quantum information Theory with the free
energy principle and proposed that
physical interaction is a form of
information exchange uh where the
holographic principle can essentially be
used to formalize boundaries between
systems uh additionally warier
investigated the potential for tensor
networks to represent um gener
generative active inference models so
tensor networks of course can offer
computational benefits When r on quantum
computers and the tensor Network itself
was originally um designed to be used uh
in um in quantum
mechanics um so specifically for Fields
approach uh with the quantum reference
frames we see it's a different way of
approaching the Markov blanket um which
still formalizes boundaries using the
holographic principle so it's still
assuming that we can properly
distinguish the boundaries between uh
you know organisms and their
environments and that these boundaries
are both causally uh necessary right so
that there's some causal impact at the
boundary uh that cannot be ignored and
that the boundary itself uh is you know
properly
distinguishable
um so now I'll just I'll go into uh some
theories of sorry the overview of
consciousness and how it's implicated in
uh both Fe and active inference and how
it fits into the proposed uh framework
for um for for uh for utilizing
entanglement so uh the minimal causal
mechanisms of Consciousness we see that
there are regions in the brain that are
implicated in Consciousness where you
know if there uh if these regions of the
brain are damaged or not functioning
properly this leads to changes in the
overall phenomenal and conscious uh
perception of individuals so we also see
that non-equilibrium macroscopic brain
Dynamics are a robust signature of
Consciousness so at some level
Consciousness uh can you know
statistically and um uh and physically
be proven to be the sort of higher order
uh um process or or dynamic that is
going on in the
brain and so uh Consciousness and the
Markov blanket so how does Consciousness
interact with the Markov blanket and the
free energy principle does the link
between phenomenal perception judgment
awareness observation Etc disrupt the
epistemological application of the marov
blanket and do competing theories of
Consciousness pose problems for active
inference so uh on the first question I
think that when when it comes to the
Markov blanket and fr energy principle
Consciousness pres you know as I guess
with all neuroscientific theories uh is
the sort of uh throw a wren in things
when we are trying to uh uh consider how
you know conscious States or differ
levels of conscious States may not be
easily or neatly put into boxes of
either internal or sensory States
because again you're assuming that the
organism has either the organism itself
has some capacity to differentiate
between these states and that the states
themselves can be placed into this sort
of uh into these these sort of
categories for representation by the
marov blanket so I think this is
especially apparent when we are
discussing phenomenal perception
judgment awareness uh observation Etc
because um these types of phenomena are
very very broad ranging in terms of
their uh phenomenal activity and their
corresponding correlation sorry their
correspondence to underlying neuronal
Dynamics um and of course the research
there is still ongoing but uh based on
you know whatever what research there is
into uh awareness for example attention
or
observation um there there there seems
to be um varying sort of uh degrees of
complexity and uh also degrees of of
causality when it comes to you know
which areas of the brain are implicated
in minimal
self-awareness and to what extent these
boundaries uh initially observed can be
modified um or you know modified either
internally by by the the person The
Observer Modified by some external uh
external causal Force for example uh
like anesthetics and so the competing
theories of Consciousness sorry do
competing theories of Consciousness pose
problems for active inference and I
would say depends on the mechanism of
Consciousness right so it depends on how
these theories lay out Consciousness
because they may or may not implicate
active inference for example uh theories
which are more volitional on the on the
more volitional side that attribute um
you know Consciousness to volitional
activity which in itself is uh maybe
distinct from you know uh free energy
minimizing um or uncertainty minimizing
activities then we would see that uh
that yes these competing theories of
Consciousness do or would Pro problems
for uh for active inference
and another Dynamic that I want to
explore here is uh the unconscious right
so experimental evidence supports a sort
of minimal unconscious where we can
broadly distinguish between type one and
type two thinking so type one thinking
is unconscious processing and type two
thinking is cons conscious processing
and um researchers have sort of found
that there is a form of dynamic
unconscious which sits between the s of
conscious processes that are you know
directly under observation or awareness
and then those perhaps autonomic
processes for example where uh they're
they're entirely uh
unconscious and so the dynamic
unconscious Theory essentially posits
that the uh The Observer or the the
conscious agent themselves has some
capacity to uh to guide their awareness
to processes that were previously um
previously unconscious so uh you can
essentially make previously unconscious
processes conscious and again the
implications for the mark of blankets uh
neat delineation between sensory active
and internal States um I would say this
this sort of frustrates uh the the um
the thinking behind Okay the thing
behind trying to separate out uh the uh
these um these these different states
right and so theories of the brain
should incorporate a transition from
unconscious to conscious awareness um
and of course this is extremely
difficult because we don't have really a
solid understanding of what would what
Consciousness even is what are the
minimal phenomenal sort of uh requisites
of Consciousness and how sort of
expansive the operations of the
unconscious are and whether those
unconscious operations are therefore
implicated in conscious processing as
well for example with uh underlying
cognitive
biases so uh what are the implications
for the free energy principle so both
conscious and unconscious processes
should be modeled however the
distinction between uh sensory and
internal states does not do uh this uh
these conscious and unconscious
distinction I think it doesn't do adjust
so why is that the case well first
conscious processes are sometimes
unconscious processes are processes that
may inherently be uh be sort of
semiconscious for example when someone
is uh is scratching their their leg for
example right the the distinction
between uh conscious and unconscious
processes is one that is fundamentally
dynamic and therefore um we don't know
whether there even is a boundary between
the awareness of scratching leg and and
not scratching leg and especially if
that boundary is uh is sort of um is
highly Dynamic for example uh when
someone is slipping in and out of
Consciousness post
anesthesia um and so we see that
unconscious and conscious processes
could influence active inference in ways
that are are particularly unique to them
so for example unconscious processes uh
could be represented as uh as you know
as priors within the model um but that
doesn't always necessarily have to be
the case because these unconscious
processes could also be interacting as
um as as internal States for example or
they could be uh they could be present
even as active States once they are made
uh made conscious um and so the
mechanisms of Consciousness uh various
uh theories which have been proposed
could provide a mathematical basis for
expanding active inference and the free
energy Principle as well so I think this
is very important to note because uh
theories of Consciousness um sorry novel
theories of Consciousness that
incorporate you know more Quantum
information side or that correspond to
um you know the electrical sorry the the
electrical um the electrical correlates
of Consciousness for example um are
extremely important for uh for sorry May
provide mathematical Frameworks for
updating um active inference or you know
potentially May provide a useful uh
mechanisms um for modeling specific
conscious processes that could then be
incorporated into uh the framework of
active
inference um and so see and so yeah so
uh I think I'm missing a few slides here
but uh basically the the the overall
theories and most promising theories of
Consciousness um uh that that are that
are upcoming are you know the sort of um
the the
electrophysiological and um Electrical
uh the electrical field uh sort of
theories of Consciousness which posit
that Consciousness is actually a result
of the electrical Dynamics in the brain
which of course uh you know would need
to be a case as as for for any minimally
causal um sort of uh representation of
Consciousness but the presence of
electrical fields and the implication of
these fields in Consciousness is uh you
know a particularly new Avenue of
research and we see that for example
firing patterns in the brain have
produced uh quasi Crystal representation
and and can be represented as well um in
in in the Taurus uh for example so these
uh higher dimensional uh uh Dynamics
within the brain correlating to
Consciousness or um or these sort of
unconscious processes will be extremely
important in um in determining you know
what processes are relevant for
Consciousness and how these might be
implicated in uh in for example or uh
thought patterns you know traversing
whatever sort of dynamic landscape that
exists in the brain which again may be
determined by these higher order or uh
these higher magnitude or dimensional
structures so um overall we see that
investigating the mechanisms of
Consciousness I think is fundamentally
necessary for uh for FN active inference
because these uh structure um or have
the potential D structure uh uh thought
and the ways in which uh certain uh you
know energy landscapes for example in
the brain are uh are traversed or are um
are fundamentally interact with each
other and so uh the areas for future
work here um would be to unpack the
philosophical dimensions of active
inference which would include implicit
assumptions about intelligence sapience
and sentience so for example you could
utilize Denny Jean's conception of
intelligence which um which argues for a
a a a uh sorry a relationship between
the model and the modeling so and sorry
the model and the modeler um as a as a
direct form of intelligence there or you
could utilize Imon Don's theory of
individuation as a more productive
method for explaining uh the boundaries
um and cellular differentiation which
I've critiqued previously uh you could
also utilize Quantum Computing to take
advantage of quantum specific algorithms
and uh to investigate uh Quantum
biology um um with an
increasing uh with increasing scrutiny
for
example and and discover ways in which
Quantum biology is implicated uh in you
know processes of Consciousness active
inference and in the brain
and so essentially the the the overall
Theory here when it comes
to when it comes to uh
oh when it comes to um to to active
inference and
uh and uh multiscalar phenomena and uh
and Consciousness is that we can
essentially um if we take that the
boundaries between the the system and
these systems are not actually uh
ontological or physically causal
causally implicated um and we utilize
this sort of uh causal entanglement to
represent relationships between uh you
know different parts of the system uh
Consciousness can be taken as a form of
observation along uh specific uh you
know um causal trajectories within the
system that would essentially collapse
the superposition of these entangled
states which would produce you know
specific uh outcomes and so that's a
very broad sort of method for
integrating um Consciousness with you
know Quantum phenomenon and entanglement
but I think that there are many uh many
many other sorry different there are
many there are different methods of
integrating quantum mechanics with uh
with the Paradigm of active inference
for example that don't just that are
that are distinct from the holographic
principle and do not rely on the
explicit representation and encoding of
information in uh in boundaries for
example um and when it comes to for
example these unconscious processes as
I've outlined in the abstract
these unconscious processes could be
represented more so by you know the
minimization of uncertainty um uh via
you know the free energy Principle as
always ongoing processes similar to
elon's argument whereas conscious and
more volitional um uh actions would be
represented by the sort of observation
on this Quantum system Where We Are uh
where we are collapsing the
superposition of specific entangled
States and so I think that in this in in
that way entanglement offers two sort of
uh sort of benefits to the active
inference Paradigm the first is that it
allows for some flexibility when we are
talking about uh different variables and
causal connections between and across
scales because we can entangle two
variables that are causally distinct um
sorry that are that are uh scale that
are that are distinct across scales for
example but which may be implicated in
some uh feedback loop for example um and
this entanglement can then uh represent
the causal dependencies between these
variables on the other hand um if
Consciousness you know is a sort of
quantum process then it would allow
allow uh it would allow for the
integration of whatever Quantum
processes that are ongoing in in
whatever you know Quantum Consciousness
uh um so if if you believe that
Consciousness collapses the wave
function for example then uh then
incorporating entanglement would be a
mathematically feasible um technique for
incorporating this uh this form of
valtion where essentially the uh the
conscious agent is collapsing a specific
wave function and that leads to uh you
know that allows them to perform uh
active inference for example by
minimizing uh specific uh probability
densities so um yeah that's overall uh
the the scope of my talk today
um and yeah I hope uh everyone uh
enjoyed that and uh if you have any
question questions please let me
know thank you
Devin great times so I'll ask one
question you'll give the closing word
for the live streams for the whole
Symposium so you're the only undergrad
presenter what would you say excited you
to get into the game and what do you say
to younger Learners to
come um um I am mainly interested
in uh um the sort of mathematical and
philosophical
um uh I
guess um ideas behind uh active
inference and um I was I'm particularly
um uh happy to see that the active
inference ecosystem has you know
thriving uh philosophical
and uh and
mathematical um Community
um so when it comes to uh
um younger
uh
um uh participants who may be interested
in active inference I would say uh you
know keep uh pursuing um what you're
interested in and um if you have any
particular areas of research or ideas
you should always um be be looking to
share them I think and uh be looking to
expand your horizons so
yeah cool well looking forward to
hearing more from you and from others so
thanks again Devon for bringing so much
together in this last Capstone
talk thank you so much for inviting me
to uh give the talk and apologies uh I
was a little bit short on time to uh to
put together the slides so uh this was a
lot uh messier than I would have liked
unfortunately but uh yeah real life is
like that all right thanks Devon peace
thank you so much